<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Books | David A. Bader</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/books/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Books</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 12:51:15 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/sharing.jpg</url>
      <title>Books</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/books/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Massive Graph Analytics (Chapman &amp; Hall / CRC Press), 2022</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/books/2021-massivegraphanalytics/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Sep 2021 12:51:15 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/books/2021-massivegraphanalytics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Expertise in massive scale graph analytics is key for solving real-world grand challenges from health to sustainability to detecting insider threats, cyber defense, and more. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Massive Graph Analytics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; provides a comprehensive introduction to massive graph analytics, featuring contributions from thought leaders across academia, industry, and government.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The book will be beneficial to students, researchers and practitioners, in academia, national laboratories, and industry, who wish to learn about the state-of-the-art algorithms, models, frameworks, and software in massive scale graph analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publisher ‏ : ‎ Chapman and Hall/CRC; 1st edition (March 1, 2022)&lt;br&gt;
Language ‏ : ‎ English&lt;br&gt;
Hardcover ‏ : ‎ 544 pages&lt;br&gt;
ISBN-10 ‏ : ‎ 0367464128&lt;br&gt;
ISBN-13 ‏ : ‎ 978-0367464127&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Graph Partitioning and Graph Clustering (American Mathematical Society), 2013</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/books/2013-graphpartitioning/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Mar 2013 13:08:48 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/books/2013-graphpartitioning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Graph partitioning and graph clustering are ubiquitous subtasks in many applications where graphs play an important role. Generally speaking, both techniques aim at the identification of vertex subsets with many internal and few external edges. To name only a few, problems addressed by graph partitioning and graph clustering algorithms are: What are the communities within an (online) social network? How do I speed up a numerical simulation by mapping it efficiently onto a parallel computer? How must components be organized on a computer chip such that they can communicate efficiently with each other? What are the segments of a digital image? Which functions are certain genes (most likely) responsible for? The 10th DIMACS Implementation Challenge Workshop was devoted to determining realistic performance of algorithms where worst case analysis is overly pessimistic and probabilistic models are too unrealistic. Articles in the volume describe and analyze various experimental data with the goal of getting insight into realistic algorithm performance in situations where analysis fails. This book is published in cooperation with the Center for Discrete Mathematics and Theoretical Computer Science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publisher ‏ : ‎ American Mathematical Society (March 28, 2013)&lt;br&gt;
Language ‏ : ‎ English&lt;br&gt;
Paperback ‏ : ‎ 240 pages&lt;br&gt;
ISBN-10 ‏ : ‎ 0821890387&lt;br&gt;
ISBN-13 ‏ : ‎ 978-0821890387&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scientific Computing with Multicore and Accelerators (Chapman &amp; Hall / CRC Press), 2011</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/books/2011-scientificcomputing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2010 13:02:31 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/books/2011-scientificcomputing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The hybrid/heterogeneous nature of future microprocessors and large high-performance computing systems will result in a reliance on two major types of components: multicore/manycore central processing units and special purpose hardware/massively parallel accelerators. While these technologies have numerous benefits, they also pose substantial performance challenges for developers, including scalability, software tuning, and programming issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Researchers at the Forefront Reveal Results from Their Own State-of-the-Art Work*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Edited by some of the top researchers in the field and with contributions from a variety of international experts, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scientific Computing with Multicore and Accelerators&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; focuses on the architectural design and implementation of multicore and manycore processors and accelerators, including graphics processing units (GPUs) and the Sony Toshiba IBM (STI) Cell Broadband Engine (BE) currently used in the Sony PlayStation 3. The book explains how numerical libraries, such as LAPACK, help solve computational science problems; explores the emerging area of hardware-oriented numerics; and presents the design of a fast Fourier transform (FFT) and a parallel list ranking algorithm for the Cell BE. It covers stencil computations, auto-tuning, optimizations of a computational kernel, sequence alignment and homology, and pairwise computations. The book also evaluates the portability of drug design applications to the Cell BE and illustrates how to successfully exploit the computational capabilities of GPUs for scientific applications. It concludes with chapters on dataflow frameworks, the Charm++ programming model, scan algorithms, and a portable intracore communication framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Explores the New Computational Landscape of Hybrid Processors&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By offering insight into the process of constructing and effectively using the technology, this volume provides a thorough and practical introduction to the area of hybrid computing. It discusses introductory concepts and simple examples of parallel computing, logical and performance debugging for parallel computing, and advanced topics and issues related to the use and building of many applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publisher ‏ : ‎ CRC Press; 1st edition (December 7, 2010)&lt;br&gt;
Language ‏ : ‎ English&lt;br&gt;
Hardcover ‏ : ‎ 514 pages&lt;br&gt;
ISBN-10 ‏ : ‎ 143982536X&lt;br&gt;
ISBN-13 ‏ : ‎ 978-1439825365&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Petascale Computing: Algorithms and Applications (Chapman &amp; Hall / CRC Press), 2008</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/books/2008-petascalecomputing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Dec 2007 12:57:11 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/books/2008-petascalecomputing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Although the highly anticipated petascale computers of the near future will perform at an order of magnitude faster than today’s quickest supercomputer, the scaling up of algorithms and applications for this class of computers remains a tough challenge. From scalable algorithm design for massive concurrency toperformance analyses and scientific visualization, &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Petascale Computing: Algorithms and Applications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; captures the state of the art in high-performance computing algorithms and applications. Featuring contributions from the world’s leading experts in computational science, this edited collection explores the use of petascale computers for solving the most difficult scientific and engineering problems of the current century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Covering a wide range of important topics, the book illustrates how petascale computing can be applied to space and Earth science missions, biological systems, weather prediction, climate science, disasters, black holes, and gamma ray bursts. It details the simulation of multiphysics, cosmological evolution, molecular dynamics, and biomolecules. The book also discusses computational aspects that include the Uintah framework, Enzo code, multithreaded algorithms, petaflops, performance analysis tools, multilevel finite element solvers, finite element code development, Charm++, and the Cactus framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Supplying petascale tools, programming methodologies, and an eight-page color insert, this volume addresses the challenging problems of developing application codes that can take advantage of the architectural features of the new petascale systems in advance of their first deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Publisher ‏ : ‎ Chapman and Hall/CRC; 1st edition (December 22, 2007)&lt;br&gt;
Language ‏ : ‎ English&lt;br&gt;
Hardcover ‏ : ‎ 620 pages&lt;br&gt;
ISBN-10 ‏ : ‎ 1584889098&lt;br&gt;
ISBN-13 ‏ : ‎ 978-1584889090&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
